[rock music]
[Peter] All right, guys,
today we're going to a different Maine.
The story of Lewiston is immigration.
Back in the day, the textile mills
brought in people from Quebec.
The Canadians flooded down here,
worked in the mills.
They went out of business in 1992.
Early 2000s, the next wave of immigration,
Somalis, mostly Somalis.
So today we're going to
get on the streets here.
We're going to talk to
as many people as we can.
We're going to canvas the town.
I was told, actually,
I think they're up there.
The streets named after trees.
They're like, "Ooh, be careful out there."
Here we have one.
Chestnut Street
in that direction to the right.
And when I looked online with Lewiston,
it was either the war zone story.
Absolutely awful.
Or, you know,
nice community going through a transition.
So this looks interesting.
Definitely not the Maine on the postcards.
Definitely not the Maine I've seen so far.
It's got beautiful architecture.
You can see it's probably the most
ethnically diverse town
in Maine that exists for sure.
Prince of Peace Parish.
Looks like they're giving out meals.
People lining up.
Grand old architecture.
I didn't get them on camera, but there are
some churches coming into town
we'll cruise out to
that were absolutely beautiful.
Got this massive park up here.
I'm showing you what I see, guys.
I mean, this girl is just…
We won't get it on camera,
but just sticking her vein
right there with something.
Okay, so you ladies aren't from Lewiston?
-No.
-How you liking it?
I've been living here for 10 years
and I don't like it. I prefer Auburn.
-Auburn's better?
-Massachusetts.
-You're from Mass?
-I'm from Massachusetts.
I was born in Mass, but raised in Maine.
Okay, what's better?
-It's called the Dirty Lou.
-I hate Lewiston.
-You hate Lewiston?
Mass, we got places to go.
We got sh*t to do.
We got transportation. And we get help.
There's nothing up here.
This sh*t's dead up here.
This is like retirement state.
-You guys call it the Dirty Lou?
They call it the Dirty Lou.
-You got a nice park.
-They cleaned it up, but they don't have
no after school programs,
nothing to help these kids stay away
from selling drugs and on the street.
-What about playing…
-No YMCA, no Boys and Girls Club.
-What about playing in the park?
-What about it?
There's not even enough f*cking equipment!
-Where's the slide?
-Yeah, but kick the ball around.
-Kick the ball, yeah.
-Okay.
All right.
You know, I think they need
more activities for the teenagers.
Especially for the summer.
It's real dead here.
I like it. It's quiet.
It's calm compared to Massachusetts
where I was born and raised.
But when it comes to activities
and staying busy
and getting
the negative sh*t out your head,
there's nothing around here.
It's stand around. Smoke and drink.
You came all the way from L.A.?
Yeah, to visit my baby niece.
-What do you think of Maine?
-What do I think of Maine?
-Yeah, coming from LA.
-Trashy sh*t.
-Trash?
-Trash.
High quality garbage.
It is.
-How so?
It's just a time difference.
It's like a time lapse.
You get here, you're like in 1992, 1993.
Rodney King
hadn’t got his a** whooped yet.
Yeah, you feel me?
Tupac's still alive.
-Tupac's wandering these streets up here?
-You feel me?
-All right.
The time lapse is just different.
-I was told not to go up here.
-No, you go ahead. Go up there.
-Yeah.
-That sh*t ain't sh*t.
Yeah, I'm not…
-That's what they say.
-I look like a cop. I can't help it.
You can't go up there
just because they say sh*t.
-Are you from here?
-Raised right here.
-Can I ask you a question?
-What's up?
How is it? What's your take?
Get me out of here.
[laughter]
Really? That's what everyone's saying.
-Get me out of here.
-Where do you want to go?
Away far from the Lewiston and the cops.
Alright, so the guy said
go up to Pine Street.
We're going to get up on
these tree streets in a little bit.
But I want to show you the downtown first.
Huge new development here.
I wonder what those are.
Look like apartment buildings.
What is this? New apartments?
-Yeah, that's new apartments.
-That's cool. You guys from here?
-Yeah, we're from here.
-How is it?
It's a beautiful…
Because Lewiston
used to be beautiful city.
I'm talking about 2010.
-It's changed since 2010?
-Yeah.
Okay, I thought the mills went away in '92
and then it went down, right?
-And then it came up?
-Mm-hmm.
And what's it doing now?
Now it's worse.
-Okay.
-It's very worse. You know why?
The people keep shooting
on the street for no reason.
And you know that gun don't kill people.
People kill people.
-That's true.
For example, right now,
me and you and her, we are here.
Somebody start shooting and I don't
even know him. Why he kill me for?
But they're not doing a good job 'cause
there's only one homicide last year..
You see on the TV.
Gang.
-You have a lot of gangs?
-Yeah. They get involved.
They come from somewhere,
wherever they live.
But the police, they're not doing…
The police are not doing a job.
Our economy is collapse.
-Not much work in town, huh?
-Nothing.
We have zero.
What we need, we need peace.
We want our city back.
-You want your city back?
-Yeah, that's it.
-Okay.
-Thank you.
-See you guys. God bless.
-God bless you.
-Thank you so much.
-Thank you.
Guys, quick question.
What's going on here, do you know?
-They're building new apartments.
-New apartments?
Supposed to be a store.
Miss Susan owns part of it.
She's gonna open a market.
-Okay. So that's good.
That's good for Lewiston, right?
Who are they putting in there?
Probably you know who.
I don't know who. I just got here.
Probably immigrants, most likely.
-You think so?
-I don't think so. I'm pretty sure.
That's what they did
with all the other buildings.
-Okay. Who's funding that then?
Probably HUD or whoever, you know.
There might be a sign.
Okay, I'll check it out.
It's probably us.
Pretty corrupt.
-Government here?
-Oh yeah.
Even the people that help.
People that help are driving
brand new Cadillac Escalades.
And they're helping the homeless.
I mean, it ain't rocket science.
-I follow you on YouTube.
-Thank you.
-I've seen quite a few of your videos.
-I appreciate it.
Reservation, middle of nowhere
in New York, the Amish.
-Thank you.
-That's how I knew I recognized you.
Yeah, my audience is everyone. It's wild.
How many followers do you got?
-I got like 53 followers.
-I'm one of them.
Can you do a wheelie on that thing?
I'll get that on YouTube.
-I can somewhat.
-Let me see some tricks.
Give it to me.
Eh…
Yeah, alright. You're getting there.
That's a tough one with the knobby tires.
-Take care, brother. Have a good one.
-You too.
Hey guys, so when I say
my audience is wide, it is everyone.
It is everyone from the 94 year old guy
that I met the other day.
I think it was 94, maybe 92.
To the 12 year old, to whomever.
So here we go. Here's a new project.
DeWitt Park.
52 new homes.
36 one bedroom apartments.
Lewiston Housing here.
The guy was saying HUD
was funding some of this.
Not sure.
Can't prove any of that right now.
Just hitting the streets like this.
Guys, here we are coming up on downtown.
We have the Daya store over there.
Groceries and electronics.
That's an interesting combo.
Got some mosque mirrors there.
Got a little bit of this
going on in Lewiston.
Some empty storefronts.
Well, there's some paint out.
That's a good sign.
Red Cap Staffing.
So probably an employment agency of sorts.
Got the Mascalai Cafe.
[car honks]
Lot of people know the content here?
Gotten quite a few honks.
And they said careful with the camera,
the guy's back in the park.
Nobody wants to get on camera.
I think there's probably been
some friction here.
Got some great old buildings.
Unfortunately,
no activity in the bottom there.
[man] What are you doing here?
-I'm doing a Lewiston video.
-Yeah?
-Are you from here?
-I am, man.
-Talk to me.
-Yeah, thank you.
-What's your name?
-Isaac Flaherty.
What's it like these days?
I'd say it's calm,
but eerie.
-As in a lot of crime, that sort of thing?
-Yeah.
Definitely not random violence.
It's definitely more violence
towards drugs
and the disturbed youth
kind of being degenerates.
-So growing up here, what was it like?
It was fairly calm.
The most scary part was probably
where the ex-police department was.
-This is Kennedy Park.
-I was just there.
The most dangerous street in the 90s,
mid-2000s was Knox Street.
-This one right here. Off the park.
-Okay.
And there would be some stabbings
occasionally, but never random violence.
Always people, bad drug deal.
Someone owes someone money.
But never really random acts of violence.
-But now you're saying it's worse?
-Yeah.
And it's mostly a youth thing?
Youth, yeah.
People will want to blame
the drug addicts, but they're
usually just zombied out
doing their own things.
Like you see everywhere
in the United States.
Luckily, fentanyl
doesn't make people aggressive.
-Right.
-Imagine if it did.
Imagine if people went on fent
and started chasing you.
Like the crack epidemic in the 90s, right?
-That would be awful.
-Yeah, absolutely.
-It's awesome you're here.
-Thank you, brother.
-Thank you.
-Thanks for watching the channel.
Alright guys, this building right here
on the main street, $225,000.
It's got a bit of a tilt going on.
But a little sample
of Lewiston real estate.
That's a beauty.
Pretty eclectic pawn shop here.
Doing everything from swords
to guitars to guns to gold.
-Absolutely.
-Nice.
-How's business?
-Can't complain.
-It's going well?
-Oh yeah. Been here 50 years.
Oh, that's cool.
Down these three steps,
if you go to the left and straight,
there's a big music room.
Alright. Thank you.
-How you doing, sir?
-Not too bad at all.
-How are things in Lewiston these days?
-It depends on who you talk to.
It's tough.
-You grew up here?
-Yes.
-How was it when you were a kid?
-Not like this.
I mean, there was people peddling joints,
but that was about it.
So you were at the end of the mill days
when the mills were in business?
-There were a lot of good jobs in town?
-The mills were prosperous.
-Where do people work now?
There's the bakeries.
Bakery is huge right now.
It's great employment.
-Oh, bakery, like commercial bakery.
-Yeah, Lepage Bakery is over here.
There's plenty of jobs to be had
if you're looking.
-Do you have a good music scene here?
-Yes, very much.
-Like, good live music?
-Yup.
Always has.
Lewiston has always been
thriving with the music scene.
This is one of the largest music rooms
really in the state right now.
-Even bigger than the ones in Portland?
-It's comparable, very much.
-That's cool.
Acoustic guitars, banjos, bass guitars,
electric guitars of all sorts.
Brand new, as well as
items coming in from the public.
You know, there's Baby Grand.
-Oh, you got a huge amp.
-What a great place you guys got.
-Yeah.
-Where else should I see in Lewiston?
-Um, let's see.
There's all sorts of places but
I mean, just walk down this strip
you'll be surprised.
-It's a trip.
-Yes, it is.
It's more diverse here
than anywhere else in Maine.
And this has changed a lot over the years.
Used to be, you know,
all apartment buildings here.
There was a pawn shop every block.
-There you go.
Nice little find here in Lewiston.
Lewiston Pawn Shop.
Amps, guitars, tons of tools.
Wonder Bread.
Looks like the big job in town.
The streets over here
smell like freshly baked bread.
Potentially pushing it out.
[motorcycle revs and drives past]
All these vents just
getting the taste buds going.
So there's an Italian deli bakery up here
that's been around forever
and really good, the guy said.
So let's check that out.
And then you can see right off
the main street goes apartment buildings.
What's up, man?
[man] Yo, man.
What's going on?
[man speaking inaudibly]
-I'm not in the military, bro.
-You look like it.
-I look like a cop. I know, but I'm not.
I was in the military.
-Where'd you come from?
-Angola.
-Angola? Wow.
-I was in the Navy.
-Can you come down the stairs?
-Yeah, I can.
Come on down.
-Just a second.
-Alright.
-You're filming me?!
-Yeah.
Are you dying here
just smelling this bread all the time?
-Yeah, yeah.
-Peter.
It makes me eat bread
all the time, man.
I'm making a video on all of Maine.
A series about Maine.
And I just listen to the locals.
Get your take.
Coming from Angola,
what's your take on Lewiston?
What are your thoughts?
Well, Lewiston is a small city,
but a nice city. I love to be here.
It's good to be here.
-Angola is beautiful, right?
-Yeah.
It's beautiful, nice country.
-Yeah, growing.
-Okay.
And then why you end up in Maine?
It's so cold here.
Well, actually, I came to Maine
because I got some friends here.
It was easy to me to come here
because they're here.
-Okay. Cool.
Different parts of the country,
there's not much people that I know.
Angola, you speak…
Sorry, bro, it's Portuguese or French?
-Portuguese.
-You speak… I got that right.
-Obrigado.
[laughs]
-Nice to meet you.
-One of my best friends is Brazilian.
Ah, Brazilian. Okay.
He teaches Portuguese to you.
Yeah. Okay, Mr. Peter.
-You were in the military.
-Yeah, I was.
-Salute.
-See you.
-Take care.
Yes, sir.
Look at these cool old buildings here.
I'm sure this was a corner store.
The owner knew everyone type of thing.
And now it looks like… I don't know.
It's a fusion of older buildings,
somewhat newer apartment buildings.
Got a little garden in town.
Is the Italian bakery this way?
Italian bakery?
No? Okay.
How is this over here?
-This guy's like custard?
-That's a raspberry almond shortbread.
Looks good. What about this guy?
That is a ricotta square.
-Okay. I'll do the shortbread.
-Yeah.
-Everyone spoke about you guys.
-Nice.
Comes to $5.39.
Let's go $30 on that, huh?
-That's what you want to see, right?
-Thank you.
What do people tip normally?
Normally, it's like two or three bucks.
-Oh, yeah?
Two or three for something like this?
-Yeah. I mean…
-That's good.
Something's better than nothing.
-But that's good.
-Right.
That's awesome. That adds up.
Take care, man. Thank you.
This place is a trip. That is for sure.
Sir, is that a mosque over there?
Not much English with some of these guys.
Some speak really well and others,
they seem like they're new here.
What happened?
They just kept parking in our yard.
People like walk in our yard.
-Oh, people going to the mosque.
-Yeah.
This lady's got a walkie talkie
and this dude's got a walkie talkie.
They've just been like
protecting the parking lots.
-Oh, okay. Okay.
It's a parking lot situation.
This is fantastic.
So, I think there's some
parking drama going on.
He was saying the business,
they were parking there.
So that looks like
one of the mosques in town.
I think it's a bit of
a hot button topic right now.
And I'm not here to cause issues, but…
How much?
-Free, free man.
-Free?
Thank you brother.
-What's your name?
-Mohammed.
-Assalamu alaikum.
-Wa alaikum salam, brother.
Where are you from Mohammed?
-Somalia.
-You like Maine?
It's good. Good place.
-You like Lewiston?
-Yeah.
You like Lewiston?
I've been traveling all the way down to
San Francisco, California, everywhere.
Good people out there man.
-So you've seen the country?
-Very nice, man.
Every country
you see good people, bad people.
-Yeah. It's called humans.
-Yep.
-See you, man.
-Take care, brother.
Why so much Red Bull in Lewiston?
Because it's the number one
beverage in Maine.
-Are you serious?
-Yeah. We sell more than water.
-Come on.
Yeah, more than Poland Spring Water
-More than Coca-Cola?
-Mm-hmm.
-Get out of town. More than Monster?
-Yeah.
-Red Bull represents.
-Yes.
-You guys work in a team, huh?
-Yeah. [laughs]
-So you sell a ton of this stuff here?
-Oh yeah. It's crazy.
Sells like liquid crack.
-Really?
-Everyone's on it.
-Yeah.
Everyone. Even the little kids.
That scares me a little bit.
You might be on it.
You're pretty charged up.
I had one this morning.
I'm always this energized.
How you doing, sir?
How's business these days?
-Business is amazing.
-It's jamming?
Oh. Hell yeah.
-You're from Lewiston?
-Yeah. Born and raised.
-You guys sell all this stuff legally
here in Maine, right?
-Okay.
-All with licenses.
-All with licenses?
Yep.
-So if someone wants to come in here
and get weed, like this new weed strain.
-Just have an ID?
-That's it.
And you don't open your bathroom
for a good reason.
Yes.
It's either needles,
break it, or all of the above.
Downtown Lewiston,
there would be no toilets.
If you find the toilets,
I would not recommend you use it.
-I'm not going to find a toilet?
-You're not going to find anything.
Unfortunately, that's the outcome
that is because of all the problems
that's going on in downtown right now.
-Okay.
Red Bull sales. How are they?
Red Bull, we are up 90% last year.
What?! Why?!
People love energy drinks.
That's the fastest growing market
in the nation right now.
Beer sales are down.
Red Bull sales and Monster sales are up.
How much is a Red Bull these days?
It depends on the size, but it starts at
about three bucks to six.
Take care, man. Have a good one.
-Have a good day.
[Peter] Take care. Thank you.
That's wild.
Red Bull sales up 90%.
You guys are really nice in Maine
with the crosswalks.
-Yeah.
-You let everyone go.
-Yeah, man.
-Love it.
Very good drivers here
I gotta say in Maine overall,
it's so much less stressful
than most places.
Okay. So we have a lot of
these apartment buildings,
and so I'm going to give you
the information I'm pretty sure of,
and I'm not going to speculate or tell you
things I really don't know are true.
So since 2001,
roughly 4,000 immigrants have come here
mostly from Somalia.
Now they didn't all just come
directly here from Somalia.
What happens often,
and this is what I was told off camera
is a family comes here,
family members in another city
and they all want to be together.
So Lewiston has been
one of those places that
just attracts families and
ethnicities that want to
be with one another.
The federal government funds
the initial refugee settlement system,
so if these were refugees back when
the Civil War
was was hot and heavy in Somalia.
They came over.
The U.S. government funds refugees
through the State Department's
refugee program.
Okay. So then once approved,
each refugee case is assigned
to a non-profit resettlement agency,
such as Catholic Charities,
Church World Service, World Relief,
Global Refuge, HIAS, IRC,
USCRI.
A lot of those.
I'm sure you guys don't know of,
but Catholic Charities
is pretty visible across the country.
The federal government
basically outsources to those NGOs,
and then those NGOs disperse resources.
How much gets dispersed?
I don't have that number.
And that's a real tough one to get.
You can't just walk up
to someone and say, like,
how much did you get,
and are you still receiving money?
In some places I read,
it's very much a temporary thing,
as in after a few months
and people are settled in,
then there's no more real money for them.
And then in other sources I've read,
there's child care,
there's subsidized apartments,
and all sorts of resources.
It's really tough to know.
And this is where I run to a line, guys.
I'm not an investigative journalist.
To really get this place,
the story of Lewiston,
is to spend months on the ground here,
and do hundreds of interviews,
and really get to
the bottom of how things work,
and the mechanics of how things work.
And you might say, well, just do that.
A, I don't want to be in Lewiston
for a few months.
B, I'd kill the YouTube channel,
'cause you guys
want to see constant content.
You know, we do three videos a month,
and the second I go on, you know,
two, three months on one story,
then the channel dies.
So we do need… I think that's one of
our big problems in this country.
Is we need more investigative journalism.
Establishments that have
the resources and the time
to go deep on the stories
that really need a deep dig on.
Because I can come in here
and make all sorts of accusations
of what's going on or claims
and act like an authority.
And I'm not at all with Lewiston.
The goal is… You knew nothing
about Lewiston before this video.
Now we got under the surface a little.
There's a ton of digging, for sure.
Look at that, though.
What a beautiful church.
Basilica of Saints Peter and Paul.
That has to be the nicest church in Maine,
'cause I didn't see
anything like this in Portland.
That is a beauty.
I mean, to build that these days,
that's in, I don't know,
tens and tens of millions.
And back in those days
when mills were running
and the money was coming through,
they just built beautiful architecture.
Like what we see on the skyline here.
-[car honking]
-[woman yells]
-Unfortunately
we're not getting that back.
We got someone yelling here.
What's going on?
-We watch you on YouTube!
-Yes, are you from Lewiston?
-We're from Auburn.
-Tell me about it. What's going on?
Well, in Auburn it's not too bad,
but Lewiston
is going through a lot right now.
-There's shootings, there's…
-Auburn's way better off, huh?
Yep. And there's a lot of ICE
in Lewiston right now.
And a lot of homeless in the park.
I see… I walked out of my car
to a needle out of someone's arm.
-Yes.
-It wasn't beautiful.
I'm not trying to put Maine under the bus.
I'm trying to show all sides.
And I'm showing this.
I mean, this is amazing.
We actually go here.
-You do?
-Yeah.
What else should I see?
I walked downtown.
I walked to this Italian deli.
-Oh, the Italian bakery. Yeah.
The churches are a big thing,
which you just saw.
-Homeless in the park is…
-Yeah.
The homeless in the park,
you should really…
-Did you grow up here, ma'am?
-I grew up in Wyndham.
-So, you saw what it was like
back in the day?
Lisbon Street was all bars.
It was a happy place.
-Oh.
-Restaurants, bars.
So, would you say, in your lifespan,
Lewiston's at its worst point right now?
-It's the worst I've seen it.
-It's not getting better?
No.
We actually had a friend
that was detained by ICE
and all his charges were dismissed.
He was trying to seek asylum.
And he had a court date,
and we went with him
because he doesn't
understand a lot of English
and all his charges were dismissed.
We stepped out of the courtroom
and he had ICE waiting for him
the second he stepped out.
So, there's a lot of that going on.
-There's a lot of ICE in town right now?
-ICE. Yeah.
-It comes in waves with ICE or no?
-No.
Or you just never know?
You never know.
And now they're, you know,
disguising in vehicles.
They're driving around regular cars now.
And Maine has allowed them to start
putting license plates on the vehicles so,
you know, if you are an immigrant
you can be standing outside your house,
walk into the store
and they can grab you at any point.
-Everyone's on board with the criminals
getting bounced, right?
Yeah.
It's the gray zone
that most of the country's on board with.
Like, been here 10 years, paid taxes,
we got to figure out something, right?
There's a major criminal element,
so I understand that part
and I agree, but it's the other people
that get caught in between the crossfires.
-Oh, I'm sorry.
I didn't come at a good time.
No, but the homeless
is definitely, um, and the drugs.
-You saw the needles.
-Yeah.
-Is this your daughter?
-Yes.
-Okay. Do you worry
about that in school? The drugs?
Well, not really in school
but walking around town sometimes,
you always have to watch yourself,
especially being a girl,
a young girl walking around here,
because, you know,
the homeless people, they're not all bad,
but when they're high on meth,
crack, whatever.
They're, you know,
they can do anything to you.
So it's just a worry for them
and you gotta worry about
yourself at the same time.
-It was awesome to see you.
-Thanks.
Sorry to go all dark on that,
but it came out and thank you guys.
-Thank you for doing what you do.
-Thank you.
Here we have Quiet City Books.
Great time to mention, guys,
I'm going to be around the country
at bookshops meeting you face to face.
Early August.
The book signing tour,
Your Fellow Americans.
New York City, Boston, Greater Chicago,
Greater Detroit, Greater Phoenix,
working on more locations.
The publisher sets those up, not me,
but I'm working hard
to get to more of the country.
Would love to see you there.
I got a QR code here.
You can scan or link down below.
Would love to see you in person
and give you a signed copy
of Your Fellow Americans.
It's all of our stories.
It's 10 stories in total.
The cool thing about it is
you can pick it up, read a story,
which doesn't take too long,
and then put it down.
It doesn't take 500 pages
of your attention.
We got some color up here.
A lot of color on the walls.
It's getting a little nicer
over here I would say, this part of town.
Lewiston does provide
a certain type of excitement.
I think it's the unexpectedness of it
that really makes it interesting.
Here you see the Bates Mill,
one of Lewiston's many textile mills.
"In 1852, the Bates Mill
started producing the cotton goods
that led to its success
as Maine's largest employer."
You can see it's all in French here,
down below.
The story goes something like this.
The Androscoggin River
powered the mills from the 1860s
to the early 1900s.
For generations this was one of Maine's
greatest working-class industrial cities.
And guys, we're gonna go
past more of these buildings,
but they go on for quite some time.
Huge buildings.
The camera is not
really capturing them in full.
But in '92, it closed because
the economics were just better overseas,
like so much
of what's happened across America.
And it put roughly
8,000 locals out of work
at the time.
And now the town is
roughly 37,000 residents.
I think at its peak,
it wasn't even that much more.
I think it was like 45,000,
something like that.
So when the mills closed
the population went down a bit.
But then a lot of immigrants
came in right in the early 2000s.
So that kept the population
somewhat afloat.
But it looks like
they're doing something here.
Bates Mill Complex.
So there are a few businesses going on.
I mean, buildings like this
are just absolutely beautiful.
Look at the granite
above and below the windows.
Just done in style.
-Look at that thing.
-[car passes loudly]
I don't even know what that is?
Never seen a car like that.
But it just keeps on going and going.
All of these mills.
Street after street.
I can't record all of it 'cause
I'll put you guys to sleep
but it just continues on.
Just think of all the workers,
all the activity.
I'm sure the air quality was bad in town
and the work was rough.
But social cohesion
as far as everyone having a job.
I'm sure strong families,
school system, all that stuff.
You know, there was probably
a thriving culture here.
Everyone filling in the church on Sunday.
And it's easy to romanticize
the old times.
That was hard work.
I don't think most people
would want to hack that out these days.
But hey, if you know no different
then It's all normal.
It's pretty much mill, church, home, bar.
So you live in here?
[man] Yep, it's awesome. I like it. It has
cathedral ceilings, nice big windows.
What's rent like?
It's more like for whatever you bring in
for your job and all that stuff.
They just run all your pay stubs
and your bank account.
They just base it off of that.
So if you make too much,
that's what this place is.
It's going to be an actual apartment.
So that'll be market cost.
-This one, market cost.
-Yeah.
But this one,
say you make $40,000 or $30,000.
What is rent like, you think, roughly?
It's probably $700 to $800
something like that.
-Okay, so it's keeping people in town?
-Absolutely.
Plus it's getting people off the streets
and actually thriving in their life.
Actually getting good jobs,
able to get cars and stuff.
-Can I go in with you?
-Yeah, if you want to check out.
I mean, it looks good from the outside.
I like how they're converting
the whole mill into something.
Yeah.
How are you, brother?
-Tyler.
-What's going on?
What's happening, my man?
-How are you, brother?
-Good, brother.
-Dude, I know you from somewhere.
-All right.
-I'm Tyler's brother.
-You are?
-Yeah, twin brother. Can't you tell?
-Are you on TikTok?
I just aged worse than him.
-You're just joshing me, right?
-I'm joshing you.
-I'm Tyler-ing you.
-Dude, I know him.
Dude, I swear I've seen your face,
though, on YouTube or TikTok.
-Quite possibly, brother.
-Or something.
-I go everywhere.
-What are you filming here?
Doing a series on Maine.
Just checking out
a bunch of cool places around here.
I think this is cool.
You got some energy coming back into town.
-A bunch of memorabilia stuff
that they kind of kept and restored.
Like a bunch of cool pictures
of like what Lewiston used to be
and like the Mills with the bird eye view.
It just goes on and on and on.
-Look at this, man.
Views from the South Bridge
and all that good stuff.
-So when did this come about?
I want to say I've been here
for close to two years.
It was around February 2026.
I think it was like 2024.
Okay.
That's when we
finally released this place.
-So are young people staying in town?
-A little bit.
-Little bit?
I don't really know too much about
any of the people that live here.
Just a few that I kind of hang out with.
-Okay.
-Did you grow up here in Lewiston?
-Oh yeah.
That's the green bridge to…
-When you're walking towards…
-Oh yeah. How was it growing up here?
It's sweet.
I mean, it has its tips,
like substance abuse, homelessness,
and all that good stuff which is not
really good but they're trying.
If they bring more places like this
around town, then people
actually will have a better chance.
-Yeah. They just got to get off the drugs.
That's the hard part.
It is.
Can I keep going with you, Tyler?
You want to kick me out?
-No, you're fine, man.
-All right.
-So back in the day,
it was just a thriving place, huh?
-Yeah. It's beautiful.
Look at the old time movie theater.
-Oh, yeah.
-I wish we could go back to those times.
Life is just what you make it,
the way that you live, you know?
So it could be rewarding
or it could be sh*tty.
It really depends on
how you take care of it, you know?
-How do you look at it?
I look at the same energy
you put into yourself and your mind
and just like the way you want to live
around you everything else matches.
Your vibes attract your tribe.
That's one of my favorite quotes.
-That's a good one. How old are you, Tyler?
-28.
-Nice.
-Where are you working?
-The Dough Company.
It's a manufacturing for pizza dough
here in Maine.
So I manufacture a whole bunch of dough.
-Okay. I smelled that on the streets.
-Yeah. This is my…
Oh, this is great, man.
Oh, this is awesome.
High ceilings.
Yeah. Cathedral ceilings, bro.
What's going on here?
Oh, it's my card streaming.
I do card streams
for, like, trading cards.
-No way.
-Yeah.
I make some pretty good money.
I think so far I made
close to $1,500 just this year
and I started in March or May.
-Okay.
-On YouTube, or what are you doing?
-Whatnot.
-Okay. Don't even know it.
-Whatnot's really sweet.
-Whatnot? What's your account?
-It's Tyturg420. T-Y-T-U-R-G 420.
-There you go.
-Okay. So you live in here alone?
-Yeah.
My bedroom's a little bit of a mess,
but it's still pretty nice.
Got a whole bunch of stuff
just laying around, but…
-Okay. And you do this
for $700 a month rent?
This is like…
-As of right now, it's been like $860.
-$860?
I just got a new job, so I have to
resubmit my W-2s, get it authorized.
Okay. So working
at the dough company, good job?
Yeah. It's a sweet job.
It's just my boss, he's 73 years old.
So he can get a little irritable.
He doesn't have much Patience.
-But it's good pay?
-Yeah. It's decent pay.
Right now, I'm making like $18.
Same as I did. I'm just waiting.
I think after a month or two, I get
another raise, so that'll be $19 an hour.
-Okay. And you like anime?
I love anime.
This is just like a little bit
of the stuff I've put up.
Yu-Gi-Oh is my thing.
That's great. You can pay your bills fine.
You live in a nice place.
Hell yeah, man. This is my first ever
place so it's been an experience.
-Right on. Thanks for the show.
-I got you.
My pleasure.
-Take care.
-You too, man. Nice to meet you.
You too.
And this is the mighty Androscoggin River
that made it all happen.
Look at the volume of water being pushed,
powering all the mills.
It's what created the town
in this modern day iteration.
We're going to go up the tree streets,
like the guys said in the beginning.
We touched on them a bit,
but go further in
'cause that's supposedly
the toughest part of town.
And then we're going to
flip the table completely
and show you a very expensive
liberal arts college that's…
I don't know if we can get on campus
but it's right next to downtown.
$74,000 to go there.
I think with housing and board,
it's something like $94,000.
Endowment of a half billion dollars.
And I forget the student count.
I'll pull that up.
But there aren't that many students
going there either.
But one of the… I don't know if it's
top tier, but it's pretty well known.
Bates College. I've heard of it before.
Hard to believe it's here.
Here we have the Franco Center
Performing Arts and Events.
"1860, 1930, Thousands of
French Canadians came to Lewiston area.
Most by railroad from the farms
and villages of Quebec.
They brought with them their language,
Catholic religion, cultural traditions,
and a strong work ethic.
And transplanted those values here.
This monument is dedicated
by their descendants
to the spirit of faith and optimism.
Which they left to us."
Yeah, so it's starting to feel
a little more French Canadian over here.
This is called Little Canada.
And a lot of the descendants
of those immigrants
that came here back in the day
live on these streets.
So they say.
I walked into a super smoky bar
and the locals told me that.
Also walked into a shop
where an Iranian guy works.
Great guy. Iranian Jew.
A lot of people don't know that.
There are a lot of Iranian Jews.
He moved from Los Angeles to Lewiston.
He likes it.
He's like,
"Not everyone's trying to rip me off
and people are nicer here in Lewiston."
I was like wow, LA to here.
How you guys doing?
What's the Lewiston story?
What's going on?
Lewiston is not a great place to live.
It's a lot of shootings.
It's a lot of rebellient kids.
It's a lot of kids
that just come to the country
and want to be gangsters
type of stuff. You know.
If you ever wanted to come to Maine area.
I would recommend going to Auburn.
-It's a more chill place.
-Okay.
There's always like fighting
between each other.
Even for the same groups and stuff.
Kids from immigrants,
people who are from here.
Just like everybody.
-So there's a lot of I don't want to say
gangs, but cliques here?
-Different groups?
-There is definitely gangs now.
-Okay.
Back then there wasn't a lot
but now it's starting to be like
a common thing that kids…
-It's like a trend.
-Try to get into a gang.
-It's a trend?
-Yeah.
There was a shooting recently
with 12 year old kids.
Like 10 or 11 of them
that had went to juvenile.
-Oh geez.
-Yeah.
For running around each other
and shooting each other.
-Man.
-Yeah.
It's pretty rough out here.
-How do you guys stay out of trouble?
-I mean.
You drive the cool car?
Just drive the cool cars, man,
play sports. You know.
-Sports is good for that, yeah.
-Play sports.
We come from a very disciplined family.
-Good family structure at home?
-Yes sir.
Right on. You're saying sir even.
That's cool.
-Sir.
-That's not even a Northeast thing to do.
Very well educated. You know.
-Cool. Do you guys want to stay in town
or bounce once you can?
-We'll bounce once we can.
-Definitely.
Okay.
So. So if you don't have
a father figure in the home,
I've been told this a million times.
It's much easier to get into a gang.
-Right?
-Yeah. It is. Definitely.
That sh*t's not gonna fly
with your dad obviously.
-Definitely not.
-My dad would spank me.
My dad would definitely spank me.
Yeah. We're following a straight line man.
-I got the cousins giggling behind me.
I'm not going to put them on camera.
You don't want to be on camera. Right?
-[girl] No.
-Okay. Okay.
You guys are gonna drop me off
in the roughest part of town.
It's definitely the roughest part of town.
-Okay.
-Yeah.
Can I go shotgun 'cause I got the camera?
Yes, sir.
You keep a clean ride here, man.
All the time.
-You love your car.
-I love my car.
Now you ladies are in on the camera.
You know that.
-Really?
-Yeah.
-I mean, in the background.
-Okay.
Okay. What are your guys' names?
My name is FC.
-FC?
-Yeah.
-Joel.
-Joel?
-Ana Maria.
-Elian.
-Elian, Peter.
What grade are you in?
-I'm a freshman in college right now.
-Freshman in college? What college?
-I go to CN.
-How is it?
It's okay. It's a community college
we have in Auburn.
So we've got
a lot of diversity over there.
-I went to community college too.
-Yeah?
-Yeah.
So I did that for the two years
and then transfer to a four-year.
That's what I did. What are you studying?
-Criminal justice.
-Nice.
What do you think about that right now?
Right now I feel like people
might have different feelings about it
because how they think about I want to
become a cop and stuff like that.
People don't really
mess with the cops right now over here.
-They don't mess with the cops here?
-No.
But you've got to realize
that not all cops are bad.
I believe that not all cops are bad,
but people don't always go for that here.
Everybody gonna have their own opinion.
-Yeah, I hear you.
Are we gramming back there?
Yes! [giggling]
-And then we've got Knox Street.
-We're recording a mini-vlog.
-All right.
-Like, right now it's calm, right?
-Okay.
But on this same exact street,
it happens, lot of things,
like a lot of shootings
and fighting right here.
-This is the rough part of Lewiston?
-This is sort of the rough part,
Knox Street.
I guess you can call this like a block.
This is like a different block.
Right now it's calm.
I don't know if you're gon' find
people to interview and stuff,
but I'm not going this is
the middle part of the worst side.
-Thanks guys.
-I got you, bro.
-Have a good day.
-Thank you.
-It was nice meeting you. [giggles]
-High five. There we go.
-Guys best of luck with everything.
-Thank you. You too.
You know what's the beauty of your ages?
You get everything ahead of you.
-Go make the life you want.
-Yes sir.
Just make sure you ask everybody
before recording anything.
-I always do.
-Yeah okay.
-No but even the streets they don't like.
-Oh here, yeah, yeah. No I always do.
-All right guys.
-Be safe.
All right take care.
Cool kids.
All right guys,
so part of the Lewiston story
is a crime story here in Maine
so I'm gonna
drop some facts for you here.
So why does it have
such a rough reputation?
Well the homicides actually the last
couple years aren't that high at all.
It's been one last year,
one the year before,
and so for having 37,000 people,
that falls under the national average.
[car honks]
Now a few years back…
What's up dude?
[man speaking inaudibly]
Get in.
Thank you.
So national average
is actually lower, believe it or not.
But in '23 there was a mass shooting here.
Two locations.
18 were killed.
The biggest mass shooting in Maine.
I forget how many injured.
And so you know, it wasn't that long ago.
Huge, huge, huge heavy event
for Lewiston and all of Maine actually.
Biggest shooting in the state's history.
It's known for that too.
So that year the crime as far as homicides
fell between Memphis and St. Louis.
So it was very high.
But it's a small town so just
a few numbers really tick things up.
But the last couple years
homicides are roughly low.
Now homicides are easy numbers
because they're quite objective.
The other crime is tougher to track.
So a lot of stuff doesn't get reported.
Depending on jurisdiction
something can be a felony.
Something can be a misdemeanor.
But in 2024 Lewiston police responded to
53,038 calls for service.
Opened 5,234 cases
and made 2,732 arrests.
Which is a lot for a population of 37,000.
So there you go.
I hope that clears things up
a little bit here with the crime.
And then there's always
quality of life stuff.
You know, there's the stuff
that you don't see on a spreadsheet.
That being the person,
you know, yelling at the wall,
throwing things at you on the street.
Just disturbances.
And quite often you just can't
put a metric on that sort of stuff.
Like, you can feel
an uneasiness in a place.
And I'm sure
especially at night, day is always better,
Lewiston has a fair amount of that
on these streets back here.
Look at these prices here, $5.63, $5.51.
2.42 pounds, $4.82.
Wow.
Pork chops, $6.62.
Even these steaks, good price, $13.34.
-So Susan, you grew up here?
-I did.
I grew up probably
five blocks down, past Kennedy Park.
-So now you own the store.
-I own the store.
Okay, so what's going on in Lewiston?
What's your take?
I mean, there's a lot of great things
going on in Lewiston.
But I'm sure you're hearing
more of the sour thing.
No, it's interesting.
I'm doing a Maine series
and talked to Mainers,
a bunch of Mainers beforehand.
When I mentioned Lewiston,
they said it's an absolute war zone
or it's a pretty great place.
Like there was no middle ground.
It's interesting because when you hear
about Portland though, right?
Just to bring up Portland,
you hear of all these great things.
So everyone should go to Portland.
But Portland actually has
more crime than Lewiston.
We are experiencing
a lot of underage kids…
Okay.
…somehow getting a hold of these guns.
And rather than having like your
normal old school fist fight,
they're shooting at each other.
It's very, very disturbing.
Yeah. When did it get like that?
It's gotten really bad
over the last five years.
-And progressively gotten worse.
-Okay.
Are there many services for kids?
Are there many services in town?
I think there are.
You'll hear a lot of people that will say
we need more services.
But I think it comes down to
we need accountability.
And we need more parents,
active parents, parenting.
Yeah, I just met these kids.
They were talking about
how tough their father was
and he doesn't let them
get away with anything.
They were saying sir to me
like I was in the South.
But you could tell
they were brought up well.
And they're like we hate the crime here.
We don't associate with it.
And then of course
I'm all over the country so common story,
without a father figure,
it's much more inviting
to get into a gang.
Because that's that father figure, right?
That's that acceptance.
I'm not sure that kids
actually go out looking for a gang.
But I think what happens
is you have those adults
that see a vulnerable situation
or a vulnerable kid.
-So they kind of steer them in.
-Yeah.
"We can do this for you."
And that's definitely happening.
So they can have them
running their drugs, running their guns.
-Because they're juveniles, right?
-Yeah.
And unfortunately the juvenile system
has not really done us in Maine
any justice anyway.
A kid would get in trouble
for gun violence
and be released to their parents.
-Okay.
-That's a problem.
-Oh, they would get caught shooting a gun
and get released to their parents?
Oh, yes. Released to the parents.
That's been going on
for the last few years.
-Come on.
So what happens is
if there's no accountability,
you're going to continue to do it.
-And it's only going to get worse.
-Basic human psychology.
Yes. And that, I believe,
is why we are where we are today.
-Here in Lewiston.
-Okay.
Is that changing at all?
I think we have seen a shift
over the last few months.
Our police department
feels like they have more support.
-Okay.
With our city administrator,
city council, the DA's office.
You know, the police
can only do so much, right?
-The DA is very important.
-Very. And the judges.
-And the judges.
Because if the DA's
let everyone off easily,
the police,
they put themselves in the problem.
-That's right.
-Put their lives at risk.
Then if they see that
person out the next day,
they're like, what am I doing this for?
-And that's how you break it down.
-Absolutely.
I dealt with that firsthand
in San Francisco.
-We had a real weak DA.
-Yep.
-And a real weak mayor.
-Yeah.
And it got so bad, DA was recalled.
-New mayor.
So we have a great DA. I will say that.
Okay, that's good.
[man] So sorry, guys.
Just squeeze behind.
Go for it. Squeeze away.
I do think, unfortunately,
COVID played a big part,
as much as I hate saying that 'cause
so many people use that for an excuse.
But, you know, during that time,
really the judges and the jail said,
we're not prosecuting anyone
unless it's like a really bad crime.
Okay.
So what happens is if you continue
to let people get away with small crimes,
eventually it gets bigger.
So I think that played a part in it too.
Okay.
-I see some development down there.
-Yes.
That building, someone in the park
said you were part of that.
Yes. What's that story?
I'll be opening a grocery store
right there on the bottom.
-Oh, cool.
-Yes.
-But the building's not yours?
-The building is not mine, no.
Who's moving in there? What is that story?
So that is one and two bedrooms.
Will these be low rent or high rent?
So there'll be a mixture.
I think that's very important.
You don't want to just keep low income
people kind of in a certain area.
-Yeah.
So I think it's important
that you do mixed use.
What should people know about Lewiston?
What do they not know?
Because it gets a bad rap in Maine.
-Yeah.
-The rest of the country doesn't know.
I think we're a service sector,
that's why it gets such a bad rap, right?
We service so many people.
If someone has an issue,
they get dumped off to Lewiston.
But the great thing is,
is most of the time we help.
-Okay.
-Okay?
We're not just shooing people away,
but Lewiston, we're so resilient.
The people are so resilient.
And I'll just share that,
you know, in this area
of Lewiston is
the most poverty-stricken area in Maine.
-Right here?
-Right here.
When someone is in need,
everyone pulls together to help.
It is amazing.
This little credit union here, when they
have a little drive for single mothers,
it is the poorest people
at the beginning of the month
that are giving the most money.
It's very interesting.
You know, I grew up here.
I even caused trouble here,
if I was being honest.
I brought my children up here.
I have asked my children
to either live or invest here.
Are you of Canadian descent?
I am Mexican.
-Oh!
-Mexicans came here too?
-Yeah, some. My mother did.
-Okay, cool.
-Yeah.
So this building here across the street,
I purchased like four years ago.
I completely rehabbed it.
It was absolutely horrible.
And I did the same thing
to that red house there.
-Okay, nice.
-Selling the store.
-Oh, is he the one who bought it?
Oh no, he's going to make it
into a bong place.
That's what everybody said.
He's going to ruin it.
We're moving down the street
into a large space.
-We're going to have a grocery store.
-Oh.
So you're selling this one,
you're moving down there.
-I got my own apartment yesterday.
-Good!
-Yeah, I'm working at the recycling place.
-Awesome!
-You know how they tear buildings down?
-Yes. Oh, wonderful.
Good for you.
-You worry this turns into a bong place?
-Yeah.
Is that what happens?
Yeah, 'cause all the stores
that their family owns is all bongs.
You know, they don't keep
maintaining grocery stores.
They might have some food
but I bet you our fresh produce goes away.
-Yeah. It's too bad.
-Patels that are coming in.
Yeah.
-Patels?
-Right.
-Are you serious?
-They're down every corner.
They bought every store up here.
-And you sold it to them. Shame on you.
-I know.
-She's calling you out.
-I will say… Oh, yeah, they do.
Oh, I will say I've tried
to pick the best person.
As far as keeping this nice,
friendly hometown store.
It's not happening. Yeah.
But the good thing is
we'll be right down the street.
[Peter] Two blocks. Right there.
I couldn't do two stores. I did want to.
-But we won't be far.
-I'll come find ya.
-That's wild. A lot of Americans
don't know the Patel story.
Oh, it's bad.
They got into hotels and then…
Oh, they bought in
all the convenience stores.
And the truth is,
is they are not personally invested here.
So, again,
this is a very poverty-stricken area.
People that aren't dealing with
their mental health.
So you're going to see
more drug addicts, more alcoholics.
So that's what they fill
their stores up with.
Crack pipes, liquor.
It's smart on a business side,
if I was being honest
but very bad for the communities.
The wild thing,
and I'm about to get into it…
-Okay.
-…is we have this town, Lewiston.
Sort of a small, compact place.
And literally, almost a stone's throw away
is a very expensive college, right?
Yes. Bates College.
-Right there.
-Do those students come into town ever?
-They actually do.
They walk on Ash Street
down to Lisbon Street
to go to, like, Forage Market, get coffee.
And our restaurants
are about five blocks down.
-But what a trip, having those worlds
right next to each other?
Yeah. It's actually quite interesting.
Bates College, I think,
is a great thing for Lewiston.
It's wonderful to drive by
and see all the students.
And it's a beautiful campus.
But… Hey, Billy.
I do believe that…
I'm just going to put this out there.
Bates College should contribute more.
-Well, they have an endowment
of almost a half billion.
That's right.
So it's like $90,000
for a kid to go to school there.
Yeah. With tuition, boarding,
everything is 90-something, right?
Yep.
I mean, the admins and stuff
are making, like, over $500,000 a year.
-So they don't contribute much?
I saw one of the mills said Bates on it.
I don't think they do.
-And you're on city council.
-I'm on city council.
And that's one thing
that I will be fighting for
is for Bates College
to contribute more to our tax base.
They're buying up
a lot of properties around that area,
a lot of residential homes,
and multi-families
to house their students.
And it comes off our tax base.
-Do they get a tax break?
-Yes.
-Because they're a college?
They pay zero.
-What?
-Nothing.
-Come on.
-But it's not a public university.
-No.
-But they get that tax break?
-Yes.
-You sure on that?
-Positive.
How they contribute,
which they feel is satisfactory,
and I don't believe it's enough nearly,
is their students
are to volunteer in our schools
or some of the inner city organizations
that we have here.
The students go and volunteer,
so they feel like that's payback enough.
But they're, um,
you know, the city is
plowing their streets,
cleaning their sidewalks,
fixing potholes on the streets
that they have basically bought
all of the property on there
that is now off our tax base.
So although I love Bates,
I think it's important
they're doing zero, in my opinion,
to financially contribute to our tax base.
I've wanted to check out a few times,
you know, sell my property, sell my store,
and spend time at home.
And I've actually tried that.
I'm most fulfilled
when I'm doing service work.
I'm a huge humanitarian but
I am huge on accountability
and having standards.
-And you think we lost that?
-Oh, definitely.
Definitely. We have.
I think we need to bring that back.
People need to start believing
in their communities again.
I think we've lost hope, a lot of people.
And until the older generation
gets their sh*t together
and decides to go back
to what we know we need,
nothing will change.
-What do you mean by that,
the older generation?
I think the older generation
really needs to, they've given up.
They've given up
on the younger generation.
-Like retirees or what?
Yeah, I think.
You know, they've lived their life.
This is a much tougher generation
for lots of reasons.
A lot more drug addiction, right?
A lot more mental health
not being addressed.
So they have given up.
They're kind of living their own lives.
Let me just finish out my life in peace.
But the truth is,
is if everybody gives up,
then there's no one there
to teach this generation right from wrong.
And that's what we've screwed up.
Some of them.
-This is your daughter.
-Yes.
-She made the calendar.
-Yes, she did.
-She's on the force here.
-Right here in Lewiston.
She's very well respected.
-Do you worry about her?
I do worry about her but
I think that if I let that overcome me,
I would discourage her
from being a police officer.
And the truth is, is we need good ones.
-She finds meaning in her work?
-Oh, definitely.
-That's awesome.
Hey guys.
-How are you?
-Are you guys missionaries?
Yes, sir.
-Any conversions in Lewiston?
Yeah, quite a few.
-Nice. Where are you guys from?
-I'm from Utah.
-Okay. I've done a full video series
on Mormons.
Oh, really?
-I respect you guys because
you pump the pavement more than anyone.
Appreciate it, man.
You got any questions for us?
-Yeah.
So how long are you in Lewiston for?
So we are not absolutely sure
how long we're here for.
We could stay here
for six weeks to six months,
but we've been here for about a month.
-Okay. Have you had
any problems on these streets?
Not so far.
-People are cool?
I've heard they're dangerous.
Generally, but just try to stay safe.
-You know what?
You guys know how to take rejection.
-You get a lot of no's.
-Yeah.
Which is a great skill in life.
-Yes, sir. It is.
-'Cause that's what life is.
-Nice to meet you.
-Nice to meet you, too.
-Have a good rest of your day.
-You, too.
-Take care.
-Have fun.
What up, brother man?
-How you doing?
-Good.
You're just fired up.
I thought you were somebody else.
-So tell me your name again.
-Peter Santenello.
-I'm Brian Witham.
-Brian Witham.
-From Portland, Munjoy Hill.
Okay. That's nice.
And I have been in this trap before.
I, right now, currently,
am doing very well.
-Good for you.
And, uh, but I know everything
and anything about Lewiston's
corruptive, uh,
addictive ways in this community.
-What do you mean by corruptive?
Drugs, alcohol.
Not corrupt as in politics or anything.
But, yeah.
I know how bad this town
can take you down.
Oh, my God, baby.
I just got back last night from Florida.
-Sorry. I wasn't going to bother you.
-No, I'm talking to Pete Santenello.
-Yeah.
-I'll be right in.
-You look beautiful.
-Thank you.
-You're a charmer.
You're a natural charmer.
I am a natural good guy.
-Cool.
-That's what I am.
-You're off the drugs now?
-I am.
-One hundred percent.
-Good for you. Keep, keep strong.
Been back and forth a bazillion times.
-Um…
-Stay strong.
I've been as skinny
and wrecked out as anybody here.
So, I never, ever look down on anybody
because I've been there.
I don't even know
where I'm going with any of this.
It's all right.
Probably sounds stupid, but…
-No, it's good.
God bless and, uh, you can get better.
You can. I've done it.
Proven it. Pete.
-Yes. You be good.
-You be good.
-All right.
-Keep at it. Congrats.
All right, guys. We're literally
two minutes from Susan's store
and this is Bates College.
Quite an expensive experience,
though I believe roughly half the students
have some sort of financial aid.
But how crazy is this?
Right up the road.
And like I said earlier, an endowment
of almost a half billion dollars.
What's going on with the tents here?
Definitely not homeless.
And it's roughly 1800 students
that go to school here.
That's it.
Summer break, obviously.
So not many around.
-Nice dog, man.
-Thanks.
-In training.
-Just to be a good boy.
Oh, okay.
Sit. Good job.
-Beautiful dog.
-Thank you.
And his name's Hulk.
-Hulk?
-Yeah.
What's going on with the tents?
I got no clue, homie.
I just showed up myself.
-Do you live here?
-I live up the road.
It's a lot cleaner than the
rest of the area, so not as much trash.
-It's like
a totally different world up here.
Yeah. Yeah.
It's definitely different.
-How you doing?
-Good, how are you?
-Good. What's up with the tents?
Oh, the trek across Maine
and some people camp.
So we're just doing a big loop.
Oh, cool.
Some people stay in the dorms,
some people camp.
-And the college lets you stay here?
-Yeah.
-That's awesome.
Yeah. We stay at St. Joseph's College
tomorrow night.
-How's it going so far?
-Good.
Sixty… how many? Sixty-eight miles today
to support the American Lung Association.
Stop teen vaping.
-Right. That's a problem, huh?
-Yeah.
I have teenagers, so…
How do you keep them from vaping?
We don't.
We try and pass legislation
to keep it, like, away.
-Is it a big problem right now?
The teen vaping stuff?
I think so. Yeah.
I'm a physician and I see
a lot of teenagers vape. It's really sad.
-You know what's interesting?
I was just talking to this woman, Susan,
who owns a supermarket.
-She's selling it.
-Yeah.
One of the problems in places
like Lewiston is the new owner comes in,
takes out the fruits and vegetables
and the meat,
puts in the vapes and pipes and weed
and all that stuff,
and you're like, it's not working.
I understand that small businesses
have to make a living.
But sadly,
it's at the expense of our youth.
-Yeah.
-But I don't know how you fix that.
-Well, you're trying.
-I'm trying.
I'm raising money for the American
Lung Association, Biking Across Maine.
Cool. I love cycling, too.
All right, guys, for 1,800 students,
this place goes on for a ways.
Beautiful buildings,
just giving you that nice
Northeast college experience.
It's like everything lifted
by getting out of
Downtown Lewiston.
Though I enjoyed my time there.
Met some good people.
It's heavy. I mean, I can't sugarcoat it.
It's… heavy.
There's a lot of drug use
and you can sort of feel it.
And then you're in this environment
and there's none of that going on.
And they're so close,
yet so far.
And it's easy.
We all do it. We stay in our bubbles.
No matter if you're in the nicest
neighborhood or the worst neighborhood,
it's just you're in your bubble,
in your environment.
And it's tough to see
the other environment often.
It could be super close by, like here.
So I don't think too many people
are coming from Lewiston up to here.
But students here,
Susan said they were
helping with some things in town,
but she brought up a good point.
Like, what can a place like this
do that's super wealthy
with such a high tuition
and such a huge endowment?
How can they help a place like Lewiston
if it's just right there?
Yeah, it just doesn't feel good today.
The combination of those two
right next to one another.
I'm pretty hardened.
I've done a lot of traveling
and seen a lot of the world.
Every once in a while
it gets me a bit. This…
Um…
Yeah, it doesn't sit right.
It doesn't feel good.
And we've got so much
amazingness in this country.
So much beauty. So much opportunity.
And then you see Downtown Lewiston
and you're like,
God, we've got some places
really limping along.
A lot of people on drugs.
A lot of people suffering.
And I would love to see,
and many of you would love to see,
more of a focus on
this from our government.
It doesn't matter the party.
Money's not a simple fix.
Um…
It's going to take a lot,
but it's important.
And to me,
the reason I want to show these stories
is just to bring attention to them
because I do think it's
one of the most important things
going on in this country right now
is the fact that we've got
a lot of people falling out.
And I don't want to be negative.
I really don't.
But I'm just telling you how it is.
[woman] We order flights. We share them.
What do you got going?
A chicken enchilada
with a red guajillo sauce.
-Rice and beans.
-Nice.
Are you living the American dream?
-I am living it.
-That's cool.
All right. Thank you, brother.
And then the green sauce is the mild.
The red one's a hotter one.
-Red one's hot?
-Yeah.
Just like, try a little bit of a chip
before you go crazy, okay?
Thank you.
All right. Chicken quesadilla.
Mmm.
Very cheesy.
Good tender chicken.
That's got kick.
What an interesting place.
Now this was
not even a full day in Lewiston.
So impossible to give you the full story.
It really is.
There's a lot to this place.
I can feel it.
There's a lot said off camera today
that I can't totally confirm,
unfortunately.
Like, I just don't know for sure.
But there's a big story here,
and in due time I'm sure it will surface.
But there's some
hoarder in charge, let's say,
that sort of has
people under their thumbs.
And then there's the…
out at the nice restaurant,
Mexican restaurant.
People having a good time.
We got a beautiful college up the street.
I'm sure there's all sorts of
other great people here
and cool things happening.
So, like all of these stories,
they're complicated,
and way more mixed up than we ever think.
So, I've enjoyed my day, actually.
I've met great people.
Susan was fantastic too at the end there.
And you gotta love people like her
really giving it.
You know, she can tap out,
not have to deal with
what she has to deal with,
but she wants to help.
And people like that
keep a community like this going.
Also, this couple here
is doing their thing.
So, it's been a cool day.
All right, guys.
That about does it for today.
Hope to see you in early August
on my book tour.
If you're in one of those cities
or near one of those cities.
More dates coming too.
QR Link down below.
And also, this is part of
a Greater Maine series.
Five stories in total.
Five different Maines.
Gonna have one of those videos
around here.
Thanks for coming on that journey.
Until the next one.
[blues music]